בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today's דף פה *Daf Pey Hey* 85, we
start a little bit a little bit before on פד עמוד ב
*Pey Dalet Amud Bet*. We had just finished a nice piece of
אגדתא *Aggadeta* relating to eating meat, and now we move back to
הלכה halacha. *Halacha* discussion. דרש רב
עינא *Darsh Rav Eina*. So the line starts with word העולם *HaOlam*,
it's about three fifths of the way down. It starts העולם *HaOlam*.
So דרש רב עינא *Darsh Rav Eina*, so רב עינא *Rav Eina*
expounded פיתחא דבי ריש גלותא *Pitcha Debe Resh Galuta* by the doorstep,
by the by the entrance of the house of the ריש גלותא
*Resh Galuta*, who was the sort of secular Jewish head of בבל
*Bavel*,
or I should say political Jewish head of בבל *Bavel*. השוחט לחולה
בשבת חייב לכסות *Haschochet L'Choleh B'Shabbos Chay L'Chasot*. If somebody שחט shecht
*Shechts* a בהמה *Behemah* for a sick person on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*,
which you're allowed to do, right? Somebody who was סכנת נפשות sakanas
nefashos, *Sakans Nefashos* and needed fresh meat. So you שחט shecht *Shecheted*,
there was no problem in your שחיטה shechitah? *Shechitah*. Now you have
and for some reason they needed חיה chaya *Chayah* or they needed
maybe a bird, maybe a little more realistic. What about the blood?
Do you do כיסוי הדם kisuy hadam *Kisuy Hadam*, cover the blood
on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* because it was it was legitimately שחט shecht
*Shecheted*? Now a question we have yet to address, and this gets
to the whole משנה mishnah. *Mishna* about not שחט shecht *Shechting* for
a כוי koy *Koy* is on יום טוב Yom Tov? *Yom Tov*,
is what type of a problem is there covering the blood? So
there's a range of problems. The most obvious is if you have
to dig fresh dirt then you're making a hole in the ground.
But that is a classic example of חופר גומא ואינו צריך אלא
ella, לעפרה *Chofeir Guma V'Aino Tzarich Ela L'Afra*. You're digging a hole
but you don't want the hole. The hole is the מלאכה *Melacha*.
It's a type of either plowing of the ground or it's a
building of a structure. You only want the dirt. So that's a
classic example of מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *Melacha She'eina Tzricha L'Gufah*, מלאכה
*Melacha* that's not required for its for its stated intent, for its
stated purpose, and it's only rabbinically prohibited. That's one scenario. But at
least that's pretty close to actual violation, although it's only rabbinic. Another
problem is is that the dirt was not set aside from before
יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*, then it's a מוקצה muktzah *Muktzah*
problem. Now of course, if the dirt wasn't set aside from before
יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*, I shifted back to יום טוב
Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*, we'll get back to שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* in
a minute, then you couldn't שחט shecht *Shecht* it even for a
definite חיה chaya. *Chayah*. Why is a כוי koy. *Koy* special? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in ביצה Beitzah *Beitzah* says well maybe when
you set aside dirt for covering the blood of your שחיטה shechitah,
*Shechitah*, you're only intending for things that really need שחיטה shechitah, *Shechitah*,
that that definitely need covering, not something like a כוי koy *Koy*
that's doubtful. So that's a מוקצה muktzah *Muktzah* case, but that's hard
to understand, like once the dirt is set aside why should it
make such a difference? But that's one possibility. The final possibility of
why you can't is
is one minute, let me just go through the reasons. One was
oh, one was a purely rabbinic concern that if people see you
covering the blood of this כוי koy. *Koy* on יום טוב Yom
Tov. *Yom Tov*, they'll assume the only reason you're covering it on
יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* is because it's a definite חיה
chaya, *Chayah*, and then they'll come to say a כוי koy. *Koy*
is a definite חיה chayah *Chayah* and they'll eat the חלב chelev
*Chelev* of the כוי koy *Koy*. Okay, so we have three reasons
why not to cover the blood. You know, one of them is
completely rabbinic and it only applies to כוי koy *Koy*, it would
not apply to a definite חיה chayah *Chayah* that you שחט shecht
*Shecheted* on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*, that if you cover the blood they'll
come to think that it's a definite חיה chayah *Chayah* and therefore
that'll lead to other negative consequences. The other reason is מוקצה *Muktzah*,
and the other reason which is מוקצה *Muktzah* and the way the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* explains it is you only, even if you set
aside dirt, you set it aside for things you know you're going
to need to cover, not for something like the כוי koy *Koy*.
And the other is מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *Melacha She'eina Tzricha L'Gufah*.
Digging a hole for the dirt, even though it's not a biblical
violation, it's certainly pretty close to one in something we want to
be. That sounds to be the most sound. And which of these
apply by the way if you שחט shecht *Shecht* a... they were
talking about somebody who שחט shecht *Shechts* a חיה chayah. *Chayah* or
an עוף of *Oph* for somebody on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* when you
needed it to. The person was sick and they need fresh meat
and you שחט shecht *Shecheted* this bird. Do you cover the blood?
So the reason that you'll come to מתיר matir *Mattir* the חלב
*Chelev* is not relevant. This is something that's definitely a חיה chayah
*Chayah* or an עוף *Oph*. The reason that you don't מוקצה *Muktzah*...
well מוקצה *Muktzah* could be relevant because on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* you
don't set aside dirt for any purpose, right? So there is a
מוקצה *Muktzah* problem. There's certainly a problem that it's an that you're
doing a מלאכה *Melacha* not for not in the way that it's
a total violation, but a מלאכה *Melacha* you're digging, you're making a
hole on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, even though it's not for the right
intent, at least that's pretty close to a real violation. So there
are all these reasons why you should not cover the blood on
שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*. And what did he say? I mean none of
them are biblical, they're all rabbinic. But what did he say? He
says that if you שחט shacht *Shecht* it for a חולה choleh,
*Choleh* on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* and you were allowed to שחט shachat
*Shecht*, we'll even allow you to cover the blood. So we'll ignore
those rabbinic concerns and we'll say once the שחיטה shechitah. *Shechitah* was
legitimate, we'll even allow you to cover the blood. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says let's keep on continuing.
No, no, no, I'm just comparing it to a כוי koy *Koy*,
so they're going to bring a כוי koy *Koy* in. I hope
I didn't confuse the case. The משנה Mishna *Mishna* says, I'm sorry,
the משנה Mishna *Mishna* says you שחט shachat *Shecht* a כוי koy?
*Koy* on יום טוב Yom Tov? *Yom Tov*, you don't cover the
blood. And I said well what are the reasons not, what is
the violation of יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*? So I gave
three reasons. One which is unique to a כוי koy *Koy*, and
the other is מוקצה *Muktzah* and מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *Melacha She'eina
Tzricha L'Gufah*. Digging a hole even for not the right intent, at
least it's rabbinic, two rabbinic reasons not to cover the blood of
a כוי koy? *Koy* on יום טוב Yom Tov; *Yom Tov*. Now
we turn to שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*. You שחט shechted *Shecheted* a real
חיה chaya *Chayah* or a real עוף *Oph* on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*.
You did it legitimately because there was a sick person who needed
it and there was סכנת נפשות sakanas nefashos, *Sakans Nefashos*. Do you
cover the blood? And here he's saying you cover the blood, you
ignore whatever rabbinic problems might generally exist, מוקצה *Muktzah* and whatever, and
you go ahead and you cover the blood on יום טוב Yom
Tov. *Yom Tov* because you were allowed to שחט shecht *Shecht* the
animal. Okay, on שבת. Shabbos, Excuse me, on שבת, Shabbos? because you
were allowed to שחט shecht the animal.
Assuming you prepared ground from before.
Presumably, right. You ignore the מוקצה problem, you ignore the fact that
maybe you have to dig a hole. Okay, that would only be
a rabbinic violation, and since you were allowed to שחט shacht, this
animal on שבת, Shabbos, we would even let you, for the sake
of doing the מצוה mitzvah of cover the blood, we would even
let you cover the blood. And the question is going to be
now: why can you cover the blood for this when you שחט
shacht it on שבת Shabbos. and you can't cover the blood for
the כוי koy that you שחט shecht on יום טוב?
Yom Tov. And you say שב ואל תעשה, shev v'al ta'aseh, don't
cover, right? Which we say by כוי.
koy. Why can you cover the blood for שחיטה? shechitah, Well, that's
presumably the logic. Once we allow שחיטה, shechita we allow this thing
which is part of that package. Right. Now, it's not an act
that's needed for the health of the חולה, choleh. but since all
we're doing is overriding rabbinic restrictions, that's the logic. Once we're allowing
the שחיטה, shechita we're going to allow you to do the whole
thing.
Okay, part of the שחיטה. shechita Yes. Then you would have to?
No, because the meat is כשר. kosher. If you don't do it,
you're only—you're not מקיים m'kayem an עשה. aseh. You could do it
tomorrow. So? I know, so you wait until tomorrow, or you don't
do an עשה. aseh. There's plenty of things the rabbis tell us
not to do. They tell us not to blow the שופר shofar
on שבת. Shabbos. They could tell us not to cover the blood
on שבת. Shabbos Okay, so it's not absolutely necessary. But you are
right conceptually, what he's saying is once we're allowing the actual שחיטה,
shechita we're going to allow the things that are associated with it.
Did you try to go like to a river so you don't
have to worry about covering the blood?
No, I don't see that would be better. Let's keep on going.
Shh, okay, everybody.
So if you can שחט shecht on שבת, Shabbos. you can cover
on שבת Shabbos, too.
For the sick person, yes. If the person needs the cooked meat,
absolutely. Okay, shh, focus, everybody. אמרו ליה רבה, Amru lei Rabbah, so
רבה Rabbah said, רבה Rabbah did not like this, although this seems
very clear to רבקה, Rivka, רבה Rabbah did not like this. So
רבה Rabbah said, אשתומם קאמר, ishtomam ka'amar,
you said an astounding thing. וישתממו לאמוראי
מיניה, v'ishtamamu l'amorai mineih, let his—question exactly what this phrase means, but
one thing it could mean is let his tongue be removed from
him. So it's a little play on the word אשתומם, ishtomam, which
is astounding, and להשתמט, l'hishtameit, which means to be removed. But anyway,
he says that was crazy. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in the ברייתא.
braisa.
Okay, רבי יוסי אומר,
Rabbi Yosei omer, כוי אין שוחטין אותו ביום טוב. koy ein shochtin
oso b'Yom Tov. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei says you don't שחט shecht
a כוי koy on יום טוב. yom tov, This was our משנה.
Mishnah. ואם שחטו אין
מכסין את דמו. v'im shachto ein mechassin es damo.
If you שחט shecht it, you don't cover the blood because it's
a ספק. safek. מקל וחומר, Mikal v'chomer, and now here's the קל
וחומר kal v'chomer how you know not to cover the blood of
a כוי. koy. And now this is a ברייתא. braisa. This is
a very strange ברייתא braisa because it makes a lot of things
like קל וחומר kal v'chomer from one rabbinic area to another rabbinic
area, and things that are not really even comparable. It's a very
loose use of the word—of the concept of קל וחומר. kal v'chomer.
I mean, the whole thing is rabbinic, so the rabbis get to
decide anyway whether they're going to say you should or shouldn't do
it. But let's take a look at what his קל וחומר kal
v'chomer is. ומה מילה שודאה דוחה שבת, U'mah milah she'vadahah docha Shabbos,
when you have to do a מילה, milah, you know you have
to do a מילה milah today, it overrides שבת, Shabbos אין ספיקה
דוחה יום טוב, ein sfeikah docha Yom Tov, but if there's a
doubt whether you do a מילה milah today, whether it's the eighth
day or not—the baby was born בין השמשות, bein hashmaishos, right? So
you don't know if today, which is יום טוב, yom tov. let's
say, is the eighth day or maybe it's only—or maybe it's already
the ninth day, or maybe it's the seventh day. You don't know
which day because it was בין השמשות. bein hashmaishos. You have to
wait until after יום טוב. yom tov Okay, so a ודאי vadai
מילה milah overrides שבת, Shabbos, but a doubtful מילה milah doesn't even
override יום טוב. yom tov. So when you go down to make
the demand less, it goes from definite to doubtful, it's so weak
that it can't even override יום טוב. yom tov. This is going
to be the analogy. Don't complain to me that this is not
a perfect קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. It's an analogy. Okay, so—is it
the secondary יום טוב? yom tov, Yes, correct.
So if that's
true, כיסוי שאין ודאו דוחה שבת, kisui she'ein vad'o docha Shabbos, a
כיסוי kisui where even when you definitely have to cover the blood,
you won't do it on שבת, Shabbos אין דין שאין ספיקו דוחה
יום טוב, ein din she'ein sfeiko docha Yom Tov, how much more
so that when it's a doubtful covering of the blood, you won't
do it on יום טוב. yom tov. If something that is definite
has to get done, will get done even on שבת, Shabbos like
מילה, milah, but if it's doubtful, won't get done on יום טוב;
yom tov something that even if it's definite doesn't get done on
שבת, Shabbos, like covering the blood—if you שחט shecht an animal—if it's
doubtful, it certainly won't get done on יום טוב. yom tov, What
does it mean if it's definite it won't get done on שבת?
Shabbos So the גמרא's Gemara, going to say: sounds like he's talking
about our case. Somebody went ahead, שחט shechts a חיה or עוף
on שבת, Shabbos. presumably even for illicit reasons, even for a sick
person, and even though you definitely have to cover the blood, you
don't do it on שבת. Shabbos. So that's his קל וחומר. kal
v'chomer. When you definitely have to cover the blood, you don't do
it on שבת. Shabbos? When it's only doubtful, you certainly won't do
it on
יום טוב. yom tov. אין דין שאין ספיקו דוחה יום טוב. Ein
din she'ein sfeiko docha Yom Tov. אמרו לו, Amru lo, the rabbis
said back to him, תקיעת שופר בגבולין תוכיח. tki'as shofar bigvulin tochi'ach.
Again, this whole thing is bizarre that we're using קל וחומר kal
v'chomer for purely rabbinic rules. But okay, a way to understand this
is we're trying to say like, what are the general parameters in
which the rabbis sort of, you know, keep their rabbinic restrictions to
prevent you from doing these things. So he says let's take a
look at the blowing of the שופר. shofar. שאין ודאה דוחה שבת,
She'ein vad'ah docha Shabbos, you don't blow the שופר shofar on שבת
Shabbos? even if it's definitely ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, right? That's a
rabbinic ruling, you don't blow the שופר shofar on שבת. Shabbos. וספיקה
דוחה יום טוב, U'sfeikah docha Yom Tov, but if it's
a doubtful, you blow. A woman is definitely not obligated. We are
working now with the assumption which we will make put on the
table explicitly in a minute that you would not be allowed to
blow the שופר shofar for a woman on יום טוב, yom tov?
obviously it's not what we say, because basically that there's a general
problem with blowing the שופר shofar if it's not a מצוה, mitzvah,
it's like playing a musical instrument and so on. So therefore unless
there's a definite מצוה mitzvah need you wouldn't blow it. So the
assumption, assuming here, which we'll say in a minute is debated that
you would not do it for a woman, but you would nevertheless
do it for let's say a טומטום tumtum or אנדרוגינוס, androgynos, somebody
who's a doubtful woman. So here he says look here I've shown
you're wrong, there are cases where when it's a definite obligation you
still don't do it on שבת, Shabbos, but when it's... but even
a doubtful obligation that will be strong enough to override יום טוב.
yom tov So same too let's say the same by covering the
blood. On שבת Shabbos. you would never do it, but on יום
טוב yom tov even if it's only doubtful you will do it
and that's the כוי. koy. So they're challenging maybe you cover the
blood of a כוי koy. on יום טוב. yom tov.
Now that was one response. השיב רבי אלעזר הקפר ברבי תשובה Heishiv
Rabbi Elazar HaKappar BeRabbi teshuvah and רבי אלעזר הקפר Rabbi Elazar HaKappar
the son of, now this is not רבי, Rebbi, רבי Rebbi is
like an honorific, gave another response why to argue that you should
cover the blood of a כוי koy. on יום טוב. yom tov
Here's the argument. מה למילה שכן אינו נוהג בלילי ימים טובים, Mah
l'milah shekein eino noheig b'leilei yamim tovim,
מילה milah is weak, it doesn't apply on... at night, night of
יום טוב, yom tov doesn't apply really on any night is the
point. So מילה milah is a weak... somewhat a weaker מצוה, mitzvah,
it doesn't apply at
night. תאמר בכיסוי שנוהג בלילי ימים טובים, Tomar b'chissuy shenoheig b'leilei yamim
tovim,
כיסוי chissuy applies at night, even the night of יום טוב. yom
tov. So כיסוי chissuy which is stronger, applies at night, maybe that
will override and maybe you will do covering of the blood of
a כוי Koy. on יום טוב yom tov because you can't make
the comparison to מילה milah because covering the blood in some ways
is a little stronger it gets done even at night. All
right. אמר רבי אבא, Amar Rabbi Abba, רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said
זה אחד מן הדברים שאמר רבי חייא אין לי עליהם תשובה. Zeh
echad min hadvarim she'amar Rabbi Chiya ein li aleihem teshuvah. This is
one of the things that רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said I have
no way to respond to this argument that says you should not
cover the blood of a כוי koy, on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
that was the argument that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose put out and
presumably רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya commented and said that's a very strong
argument I have no way to reject it. והשיב רבי אלעזר הקפר
ברבי תשובה V'heishiv Rabbi Elazar HaKappar BeRabbi teshuvah and רבי אלעזר הקפר
ברבי Rabbi Elazar HaKappar BeRabbi gave a way to reject it. Okay.
So there's the whole little ברייתא braisa which is arguing not our
question about שחיטה shechita on שבת, Shabbos. arguing about שחיטה shechita. a
כוי koy on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Does the doubtful need to
cover the blood is that enough to allow you to do it
on יום טוב? Yom Tov? Remember again that the יום טוב Yom
Tov problem is only rabbinic. Either it's מוקצה or it is worst
case scenario you're digging a new hole fresh dirt but even that
because you're not doing it for the sake of a hole is
only a rabbinic problem. So the question here is should we allow
the Rabbis to not stand on their rabbinic restriction on יום טוב
Yom Tov. to allow you to cover the blood of a כוי?
Okay. So it's really a rabbinic question. So we're going to make
a comparison to other rabbinic issues. Okay so the funny thing is
that we start with a שבת Shabbos issue which is clearly ברית
מילה bris milah is clearly a biblical concern about violating שבת Shabbos,
by ברית מילה. bris milah. But the point is something like ברית
מילה bris milah which when you definitely have to do it you
do it on שבת, Shabbos if you only doubtfully have to do
it you don't even do it on יום טוב. Yom Tov, So
that should be our model. If you only doubtfully have to cover
the blood of a כוי don't do it on יום טוב Yom
Tov. even though it's only a rabbinic concern. And now we try
to contradict that by two examples. One a doubtful שופר shofar you'll
do on יום טוב Yom Tov, and number two is maybe
covering the blood is stronger since it applies at night and we
should allow it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So the whole question
is do we allow a doubtful covering of the blood on יום
טוב Yom Tov. by the כוי? But in the middle of that
we mentioned that a definite covering of the blood you won't do
on שבת Shabbos, and that seems to get to our issue of
somebody who שחט shechted on שבת. Shabbos, So let's take a look.
קתני מיהא, Katani miha, we teach nevertheless כיסוי שאין ודאו דוחה שבת,
chissuy she'ein vadau dochei Shabbos, that a definite covering of blood you
still will not do on
שבת. Shabbos מאי ודאו דכיסוי Mai vadau dechissuy what's the case of
a definite covering of the blood דלא דחי שבת delo dachi Shabbos
that doesn't override שבת? Shabbos? לאו השוחט לחולה בשבת Lav hashocheit l'choleh
b'Shabbos is it not that you had a שחיטה shechita for a
sick person and you definitely you were allowed to and you have
blood and you definitely have to cover it and nevertheless it's saying
you don't do it on שבת? Shabbos? So that seems to be
exactly our case and you see it's against what was said before.
So the גמרא Gemara says
ודילמא v'dilma no maybe not. ודילמא דעבר ושחט. V'dilma d'avar v'shachat. Maybe
it means that the person transgressed and שחט shechted on שבת. Shabbos.
He forgot it was שבת, Shabbos, he accidentally שחט shecht on שבת.
Shabbos. So that's when you don't cover the blood on שבת. Shabbos,
But maybe if somebody did it legitimately, there's a סכנת נפשות, then
you would. דומיה
דמילה, Dumya d'milah, just... no the גמרא Gemara says no that can't
be because we're making a comparison to ברית מילה. bris milah. מה
מילה ברשות אף כיסוי נמי ברשות. Mah milah birshus af chissuy nami
birshus. The same way it spoke about you know it said מילה
milah the definite you override שבת Shabbos the doubtful not, שחיטה shechta.
the definite does not override שבת, Shabbos. so if we're doing it
in comparison to מילה milah we're talking about a legitimate שחיטה shechita,
not an illegitimate שחיטה. shechita, So this ends the previous discussion. There's
a... meaning that if you שחט shechted on שבת Shabbos legitimately because
there was a סכנת נפשות, we would allow you to finish up
and cover the blood, again remembering that the only problem of covering
the blood is rabbinic. And the point is this ברייתא braisa makes
it clear, takes it for granted, not that way. Says, does a
whole discussion that which assumes that a definite covering of blood is
not done on שבת, Shabbos, and presumably even when the שחיטה shechta
was done legitimately. So that rejects that idea. If you did it
on שבת, Shabbos, sorry, even if it was legitimate, you'll wait to
cover the blood until tomorrow. Yes.
This once in terms of the דחיה decheh for covering of the
blood. Covering of the blood is like a completely separate מצוה mitzvah
from שחיטה. shechita Right, right. And is no longer צורך? tzorech?
Correct,
which is why we don't do it. Right, exactly. The only reason,
the only reason we would have considered doing it on שבת Shabbos.
is we would have said, since it's rabbinic, as that's why I've
been stressing that it's rabbinic. If it was biblical, there'd be no
question. You wouldn't do it because it's not part of, you know,
it's a מצוה mitzvah after the שחיטה, shechita but it's not מעכב,
me'akeiv, it's not needed for the חולה. choleh But given that it's
only rabbinic, and given that we're allowing you to do the שחיטה,
shechita. maybe we would allow you to, you know, wrap it up.
You could even make it a psychological point, that if we tell
somebody you can שחט for this חולה choleh, but you can't cover
the blood, they're going to hesitate. They're going to say, oh, so
it's not really fully permissible for me to be doing this, because
they're not going to let me cover the blood. Maybe I shouldn't
שחט for the חולה, choleh, right? And we know that particularly things
that are concerns of health and what and חולה, you know, we
want to, we don't want there to be any even psychological impediments.
But right, that was, that was, but that's exactly why we're dealing
here with rabbinic. Nevertheless, we still say you don't do it. Okay.
Now we go back.
How do we wait for, wait until after שבת? Shabbos
Why do we not wait till after שבת?
Shabbos Well, that's what you do end up doing. You do wait
till after שבת. Shabbos You mean why is that such like a
big deal, is your point. Meaning that's למעשה l'maiseh what we do.
If you say don't cover it on שבת, or don't cover the
כוי on יום טוב, Yom Tov. when are you going to do
it? You'll do it tomorrow. So you're just saying, so like what's
the big deal? Yeah, I know, it's a good point. It's not
like, you know, ברית מילה bris milah on the eighth day that
you're מבטל mivatel the מצוה. mitzvah. I mean, there is a concern
that if you wait and if it gets covered up inadvertently, you
no longer have the מצוה. mitzvah. It gets absorbed. Right, that's actually
a good question about draining, right, if it's, if it's no longer
wet, if there's just the stain of it, right, then maybe, right,
then maybe, then maybe it would no longer be the מצוה. mitzvah.
Right, I think the concern is whether you'll still have the opportunity
afterwards. But you're absolutely right. That's what you do. You wait and
you do it afterwards if it's still able to be done.
Is it part of שחיטה shechita. הכל כך, ha-kol-kach, if you're saying
that,
yeah, but it doesn't have to be right, although the תורה Torah
says ושפך וכסהו, v'shafach v'chisahu, it does not have to be without
interruption. It actually, you know, it can be, you know, anytime.
So when we talk about שחיטה shechita. in the boat, you don't
have any options. What do you do? You do it into a
cloth and then later reconstitute the blood from the cloth and then,
right.
Okay, that wasn't in the גמרא, Gemara but yes.
Anyway, so we're talking about the ברייתא braisa
that
you do not do it, you don't do it on שבת. Now
that we've established you don't do it on שבת, let's finish up
this ברייתא. braisa. Okay. אמרו לו, Amru lo,
so now we're going to look at the ברייתא. braisa. תקיעת שופר
בגבולין תוכיח שאין דבר דוחה שבת. Tekias shofar bigvulin tochiach she-ein davar
docheh Shabbos. You don't blow the שופר shofar on שבת בגבולין, bigvulin,
וספיקה דוחה יום טוב, u-sfeka docheh Yom Tov, but you do a
doubtful blowing on יום טוב. Yom Tov מאי ספיקה? Mai sfeka? What
doubtful blowing of שופר shofar do you do on יום טוב? Yom
Tov אילימא ספק חול ספק יום טוב, Ileima safek chol safek Yom
Tov, the second day of ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, like you don't
know if it's, if it's, you know, יום טוב Yom Tov. or
חול, chol, actually the first day too. Anyway, the whole idea of
ספיקא דיומא sfeka d'yoma that we don't in, that we sort of
act as if we don't know which day is the real day.
So one minute. That doesn't prove anything. I mean, not doesn't prove
anything. The logic is the opposite. The ספק safek there is whether
it's really יום טוב. Yom Tov. So the doubt there is not
whether you have a strong enough motive to override יום טוב, Yom
Tov but whether you even have a problem to begin with. It
might not even be יום טוב. Yom Tov So the גמרא Gemara
says, השתא ודאי יום טוב דחיא, Hashta vaday Yom Tov dachya, if
blowing the שופר shofar can override a when it's definitely יום טוב,
Yom Tov, ספק יום טוב ספק חול מיבעיא, safek Yom Tov safek
chol mi-ba'ya, how much more so should it override doubtful יום טוב.
Yom Tov, That's not the doubt point. We want the doubt to
be in how obligatory it is, not in how much of a
problem there is. That's obvious. So where do we say that a
doubtful תקיעה teki'ah overrides? There has to be a doubt in whether
you have to blow. So top of פה עמוד א, pei-hei amud
aleph, אלא, Ela, so what are we talking about? ספק איש ספק
אשה. safek ish safek isha. It's a doubtful somebody who's a טומטום
tumtum ואנדרוגינוס, v'androgynous, you don't know if it's a man or a
woman. And therefore you don't know if you're obligated. And therefore this
is assuming that for a definite woman, you would not blow on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Why not? Presumably the simple reason is is
because when it's not part of the מצוה, mitzvah, blowing is considered
to be playing a musical instrument and therefore forbidden again, it's all
rabbinic, but forbidden rabbinically on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So and again,
so if we're trying to argue, can you rabbinically allow, can you
allow the rabbinic restriction of covering the blood, we'll say, well look,
we allow the rabbinic restriction of blow, of not blowing a שופר,
shofar, you know, on a, without a reason, we're going to allow
it for a doubtful obligation for this doubtful man, doubtful woman, and
therefore we should allow the covering of the blood, we should allow
that rabbinic restriction as well.
Now, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on to say for רבי
יוסי, Rabbi Yose, now why was it רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose who
use שופר shofar at, who is not bothered with the שופר shofar
example? You know, why was he not bothered with the שופר shofar
example? That shows that sometimes we will override a rabbinic restriction on
יום טוב Yom Tov. even for a doubt. So he goes לטעמיה,
l'taimei, he goes according to
He says because I would let even a woman blow שופר shofar
on יום טוב Yom Tov. or blow שופר shofar for a woman
on יום טוב. Yom Tov Why? דתניא, detanya, here רבקה, Rivka, this
is a favorite סוגיא sugya of yours I think. בני ישראל סומכין
ולא בנות ישראל סומכות. Bnei Yisrael somchin velo bnot Yisrael somchot.
Only men can do, it says דבר אל בני ישראל, daber el
bnei Yisrael, right, speak to the children of Israel and we decide
there to say that it means only the masculine. Only men can
do סמיכה smicha on a קרבן, korban, put lay their hands on
a קרבן korban and not women. רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים, Rebbi
Yossi veRebbi Shimon omrim, Rebbi Yossi and Rebbi Shimon say נשים סומכות
רשות. nashim somchot reshus. It, they are allowed to. Now what exactly
does allowed mean? I mean we know what allowed means, but what
does allowed signify that it's significant here? One thing that it signifies
is that we will allow it even to override particular rabbinic concerns.
So there's a rabbinic concern that if you put your hand on
a קרבן, korban, you it would be considered and you put your
weight on a קרבן, korban, which is what you have to do
by סמיכה, smicha, it would you're supporting yourself with the קרבן korban
although that's not your intent, but that's like using קרבנות. korbanot. And
if you don't have a מצוה mitzvah to do it would be
like you're using it for your own purpose. So therefore we say
since women are allowed to, we're not going to let our self,
we're not going to concern ourselves with this potential rabbinic problem. By
analogy here, even if there's a problem about playing a שופר shofar
when there's no מצוה, mitzvah,
we're not going to you know, women are allowed to, we're not
going to concern ourselves with this rabbinic problem. Now the better way
to say it, what I've just said is just okay for the
sake of allowing women to participate we're going to ignore rabbinic issues,
that actually is the way one of the ראשונים Rishonim says it,
the ראב"ן, Ra'avan, but the better way to say it and this
is I think implicit in the אור זרוע Or Zarua is that
what רשות reshus really means is it means that women it's not
like when they do it it's a meaningless act. It means that
women are not obligated to do it, but if they opt to
do it, it's like they have an exemption but they can waive
their exemption. And if they opt to do it they are being
מקיים mekayem a מצוה. mitzvah. They're actually fulfilling even at the biblical
level a מצוה. mitzvah. So they're fulfilling a מצוה. mitzvah. They're not
obligated to do the מצוה mitzvah but when they do it they're
fulfilling a מצוה. mitzvah. Once they're fulfilling a מצוה, mitzvah, so of
course you can blow for them on יום טוב. Yom Tov It's
not playing a musical instrument. For women it's also a מצוה, mitzvah,
not an obligatory מצוה, mitzvah, but it's a מצוה. mitzvah. Of course
they can put their hands on the קרבנות. korbanot. It's not a,
it's not misusing a קרבן korban the same way it's not for
men. It's not an obligation but when they're doing it they're not
doing a neutral act, they're actually doing a מצוה mitzvah act. And
that I would say certainly for אשכנזים Ashkenazim that actually plays a
role in why there was a big debate in between primarily אשכנזי
Ashkenazi and ספרדי Sephardi ראשונים Rishonim whether when women do a מצוה
mitzvah that they're not obligated to do they make a ברכה bracha
or not. Can they say אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו? asher kidshanu bemitzvotav
vetzivanu? They're not commanded right if they're not obligated. So the אשכנזים
Ashkenazim said they can and one of the strongest articulations of why
is because that even though they're not obligated, it's still a מצוה
mitzvah for them and when they do it they're still being מקיים
mekayem a מצוה. mitzvah. And I should by the way say that
it's actually true, you know, ספרדי Sephardi women if we're coming up
to this period and you can ask them, at least I have
and this is what I've heard, they you know the I remember
I was once at a ספרדי Sephardi house and I was taking
לולב lulav or whatever and I said to the woman there do
you want to take לולב? lulav? And she said why should I?
You know, or same thing like sitting in the סוכה. sukkah. If
you're not making a ברכה bracha then the message you're basically sending
yourself also and everyone else is that this is a totally neutral
act, it's not a מצוה mitzvah act. So the making of the
ברכה bracha is sort of very important in terms of that framing.
And one certain way to understand רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi is that
he is saying that point, that they're not they're not obligated, but
when they can opt to do it and when they opt to
do it they're doing a מצוה. mitzvah. So therefore we've said that
therefore רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yossi, the argument is oh look, you know,
we do override יום טוב Yom Tov, for doubt, we override יום
טוב Yom Tov for blowing a שופר shofar for a doubt a
person who's a doubtful man. רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi says that doesn't
prove anything to me. I think even women blow the שופר shofar
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, I think it's a מצוה mitzvah for
women or it's a רשות reshus or whatever and therefore that doesn't
prove anything to me. מרדכי, Mordechai, you had...
I was just wondering how you can even bring the other conceptual
framework of רשות reshus
to allow for the blowing on יום טוב, Yom Tov meaning if
רשות reshus means just that oh they can do it because it
makes them feel good, right? Then then what would the conceptual...
well there's a space between makes them feel good and a קיום
מצוה. kiyum mitzvah. For the sake of let's say for the sake
of religious of religious participation and inclusiveness. Okay, but okay, go on.
Right,
how could you override a דרבנן? derabbanan? So that's exactly what the
ראב"ן Ra'avan says. Since it's only דרבנן derabbanan
therefore for the sake of you know this נחת רוח nachas ruach
and allowing them to be more involved and participate or whatever, we
will override rabbinic restrictions.
So the logic of נחת רוח nachas ruach could be applied across
the board to דרבנן, derabbanan, so it's a... maybe it could.
But not any נחת רוח. nachas ruach.
It's not just to say it's gotta be reserved for someone...
no no, it's not just, okay it's not time to get into
this this is not our primary סוגיא, sugya, but the short answer
is it's not סתם stam to make somebody feel good, it's for
somebody who is feeling sort of excluded, religiously excluded. So for the
sake of allowing them to participate as men and to not allow
them and that they should not feel you know a sense of
religious exclusion, for that we override דרבנן. derabbanan. That's the way the
ראב"ן Ra'avan understands this, not because that there's a קיום מצוה kiyum
mitzvah here. Yeah,
okay I know we could spend a whole next hour on this,
go ahead. Two short comments and then we're going to move on.
Yes, it's very sensible.
It shows that the rabbis
applying the... Led them to an immoral and unethical position that they
then had to
exclude. Precisely.
Okay, Rivka.
That requires no comment.
The women's blowing שופר, shofar, considering that today women at the כותל
Kotel are not permitted to blow שופר shofar by שמואל אליהו, Shmuel
Eliahu, actually not even in the עזרת נשים. ezrat nashim. Right.
Is there any evidence that in the time of the גמרא Gemara,
women blew שופר? shofar?
Because it
says a woman is permitted to blow. Right, right. It's not clear
in this גמרא Gemara, whether it's assuming that a woman would blow
for women or a man would blow for women. But
תוספות... Tosafot... ודאי, vaday, you're right, you're right. The simple sense of
the גמרא Gemara is that a woman would blow. Sure, there's no
difference between... in the גמרא, Gemara, a lot of the things that
people are dealing with today—we mentioned this the other day, no, I
was having another conversation—but a lot of things that people raise today
around some of these issues about women doing, which have to do
more with a sense of certain people's sense of propriety about things
women should be doing or not in ritual areas or whatever. In
the גמרא, Gemara the גמרא Gemara sort of ignores all of that.
Deals with all those issues in very strict halachic questions. Are you
obligated, are you not obligated, are there דרבנן d'rabanan problems, are there
not דרבנן d'rabanan problems? So yeah, you're right. In the גמרא, Gemara.
the גמרא Gemara makes no... reality... yeah, yeah, a woman could blow.
Right, right. But the גמרא Gemara is not making this... right. If
a woman is, if we rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose that
נשים תוקעות רשות nashim tok'ot reshut or סומכות רשות, somchot reshut, then
a woman can blow on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. That's definitely the
point of the גמרא. Gemara Okay, let's finish this up. אמר רבינא:
Amar Ravina: ולמאי דקאמרי רבנן נמי איכא פירכא. ul'mai d'ka'amri Rabbanan nami
ika pircha.
Even the response back
of, even without רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, there's a response back about
why תקיעת שופר tkiyat shofar is not evidence that a doubt overrides,
that a doubtful מצווה mitzvah overrides יום טוב. Why? מה לתקיעת שופר
שכן ודאה דוחה שבת במקדש? ma l'tkiyat shofar sheken vadah docha Shabbos
be'Mikdash?
Because שופר shofar has a power that maybe gives it a special
strength to override, because we know that you would blow the שופר
shofar in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash even on שבת. Again, this
is all within rabbinic problems, but we would allow it even on
שבת in some cases. So since we would even allow it on
שבת, then a doubtful case we'll allow on יום טוב. תאמר בכיסוי
דליתא כלל. Tomar bekisui d'leisa klal.
Covering blood we never do on שבת, so therefore we won't allow
it on doubtful cases on יום טוב. That's the issue about שופר.
shofar. How about the issue about רבי אלעזר הקפר Rabbi Elazar HaKappar
about night? השיב רבי אלעזר הקפר ברבי: Heishiv Rabbi Elazar HaKappar b'Rebbi:
מה למילה שכן אינה נוהגת בלילי יום טוב? ma l'mila sheken einah
noheget b'leilei Yom Tov?
מילה mila is weaker, it doesn't apply on night. And therefore a
doubtful מילה mila doesn't override יום טוב. גמרא Gemara says: בלילי ימים
טובים הוא דלא נהגה, בשאר לילי נהגה? b'leilei yamim tovim hu d'lo
nahaga, bishar leilei nahaga? What, it doesn't apply the night of יום
טוב but it applies on other nights? Because I was already rereading
it. So what does that mean, it doesn't apply on יום טוב
night? אלא, okay, fine. מה למילה שכן אינה נוהגת בלילות כבימים. ma
l'mila sheken einah noheget b'leilos k'bayamim. You're right. What it really means
is מילה mila doesn't apply at night as equal to the day;
it doesn't apply at night. תאמר בכיסוי שנוהג בלילות כבימים. Tomar bekisui
shenoheg b'leilos k'bayamim.
Covering the blood applies at night, and therefore even if you don't
do a doubtful מילה mila on יום טוב, you might do a
doubtful covering up of the blood. אמר רבי אבא: Amar Rabbi Abba:
זה אחד מן הדברים שאמר רבי חייא אין לי עליהם תשובה. zeh
echad min hadvarim she'amar Rabbi Chiya ein li aleihem tshuva. רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya said I had no way to respond to רבי יוסי'ס
Rabbi Yose's position of not covering the blood, והשיב רבי אלעזר הקפר
ברבי תשובה. ve'heishiv Rabbi Elazar HaKappar b'Rebbi tshuva. רבי אלעזר הקפר Rabbi
Elazar HaKappar
gave a good response. So it's quite interesting, right? We spent... so
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose in our משנה Mishnah just says very סתם,
stam, don't cover the blood of a כוי. Now we're finding out
from a ברייתא Baraita that it was רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yose's position,
that there actually were some opposed, strong oppositions to it. In the
end the whole problem of covering the blood on יום טוב by
a non, if even if you did have to do it, at
most you're dealing with a דרבנן d'rabanan problem. There are arguments that
even that דרבנן d'rabanan possible concern is overridden for the sake of
this doubtful מצווה. mitzvah. And nevertheless, and even though there are arguments
to say you do it, you don't do it. And one of
the reasons to say not to do it, which is not
an innate problem, is what the גמרא Gemara in ביצה says, which
is if we allow you to cover the blood of a כוי
on יום טוב, people will think, "Oh my God, he's even covering
the blood, it must be a real חיה." And if they think
it's a real חיה, then they'll come to allow to eat the
חלב of the כוי. So it really was not an innate יום
טוב restriction prevented covering the blood. There the possible מצווה mitzvah would
have allowed it to override. But it's a special דרבנן, d'rabanan, a
new rabbinic concern that we can't allow it because it will send
wrong signals about the nature of the כוי. And you certainly don't
cover it on שבת. The idea that you would cover it on
שבת if you were allowed to שחט, we completely reject. Okay, so
with that we end... that's the discussion about the כוי. We had
about two weeks ago a whole discussion about the nature of a
כוי. Here we have applying it to covering the blood. But maybe
you should be able to because it's only a דרבנן d'rabanan problem
and it's a doubtful מצווה. mitzvah. But in the end the סתם
משנה stam Mishna says that you do not. Now we move on
to the next משנה mishna and we get to revisit yet another
topic about שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita she'eina r'uya, but the approach is
a little different than we're used to than we had seen before.
Yes.
כוי. Even a כוי, yeah, כוי
on שבת you wouldn't cover the blood.
Correct. Even a ודאי vadai on שבת you don't cover the blood.
Correct. Let's take a look at the next משנה.
Mishnah השוחט ונמצא טריפה, Hashochet venimtza treifa, so classic beginning of these
משניות mishnayos about שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechita she'eina re'uya. You slaughtered and
then you discovered that the animal is a טריפה, treifa, or you
slaughtered it as an act of worship to עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
or you slaughtered—and then you all of a sudden did תשובה teshuva
and wanted to cover the blood. והשוחט חולין בפנים Vehashochet chullin bifnim
or somebody else wanted to cover the blood. Anyway, or somebody slaughtered
a חולין chullin inside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or קדשים בחוץ
kodashim bachutz or a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
By the way, that seems to have been taken somewhat as a
stock phrase because we were already taught in
the first משנה Mishnah that כיסוי הדם kisuy hadam does not apply
to קרבנות. korbanos. So who cares that it's a קרבן korban outside
the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? כיסוי הדם doesn't apply to קרבנות. korbanos.
Anyway, חיה ועוף הנסקלים chayah ve'of haniskalim or it was a bird
or a חיה that is going to be stoned. Right, normally you
talk about a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, but here you have—it's not
a שור shor because it's only about a חיה or a bird.
But you have a bird or a חיה that's attacked somebody. You
can certainly imagine it by a חיה. Well, I don't know. You
have to find a כשר kosher חיה that was violent. But okay,
I get it. A deer stomped on somebody or a
bird, like a—again, you'd need a כשר kosher violent bird, but anyway,
you'd need a כשר kosher one. Anyway, okay, anyway, anyway,
it killed someone. So now they have to be stoned. So all
these are things that cannot be eaten. Either they're forbidden in benefit,
which is most of the cases there—עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you would
stone them, etc.—or at least they're forbidden to be eaten, like the
טריפה. treifa. So it's a שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita she'eina re'uya, a
שחיטה shechita. that cannot translate into eating the meat. So what's the
story? רבי מאיר מחייב. Rabbi Meir mechayev. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
you still have to cover the blood, וחכמים פוטרין vachachamim potrin and
the sages exempt. השוחט ונתנבלה
בידו, Hashochet venisnavla beyado, if you slaughtered accidentally you made it a
נבלה, neveilah, you messed up your שחיטה. shechita הנוחר והמעקר Hanocher vehame'aker
or you intentionally strangle or rip out the סימנים. simanim. You violently
killed the animal without שחיטה. shechita. So it wasn't even an act
of שחיטה. shechita. פטור מלכסות. Patur milichasos. Everybody agrees you don't. You
need an act of שחיטה. shechita The question is, what if the
שחיטה shechita is not ראויה? re'uya? It was the right act, but
it did not make the meat permissible. Now you will notice that
when we learned that before by אותו ואת בנו, Oso Ve'es Beno,
וחכמים vachachamim said that even though it's אינה ראויה eina re'uya it
still counts as שחיטה. shechita Here, when we're talking about covering the
blood, וחכמים vachachamim were the ones that were saying that it does
not count as שחיטה. shechita? So in one פרק, perek, רבי Rebbi
sort of made—sort of gave weight to the position that it counts,
this שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina re'uya by אותו ואת בנו. Oso
Ve'es Beno. Here he gave weight to the position that it doesn't
count. And that's—the גמרא Gemara is going to be the first thing,
hold on—the first thing that the גמרא Gemara is going to deal
with. Let's take a look. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, so רבי חייא
בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba says in the name of רבי
יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: ראה רבי דבריו
של רבי מאיר באותו ואת בנו. Ra'ah Rebbi devarav shel Rabbi Meir
b'Oso Ve'es Beno. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir agreed, saw, agreed with the
position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that a נעשה שחיטה na'aseh shechita
still counts by the prohibition of אותו ואת בנו. Oso Ve'es Beno.
ושנאה בלשון חכמים. Ushna'ah bilshon chachamim.
So when he taught it over there in the last פרק, perek,
he said 'the sages say'. But really, it was always a debate
of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says this type of a שחיטה shechted counts, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says it doesn't. In one פרק, perek, רבי Rebbi said
the sages say it doesn't count—it does count—that was the last פרק.
perek. In this פרק, perek, he says the sages say it doesn't
count. So who gets to be the sages? The one that רבי
Rebbi agrees with. Okay, so in the last פרק perek he agreed
with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, so he said 'the sages say' that
it does count. ושנאה בלשון חכמים. Ushna'ah bilshon chachamim. And
in this פרק perek he agreed with רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
he said 'the sages say' it doesn't count. Now we're going to
spell out how that's split. ורבי שמעון
בכיסוי הדם, V'Rabbi Shimon b'kisuy hadam, and he agrees with רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon when it comes to covering the blood. ושנאה בלשון חכמים.
Ushna'ah bilshon chachamim. So in this פרק, perek, the sages said it
did not count, like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Okay, מאי טעמא. Mai
ta'ama. Now we're going to spell this out. מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר
באותו ואת בנו? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Meir b'Oso Ve'es Beno? What's the
reasoning of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir by אותו ואת בנו Oso Ve'es
Beno that such a שחיטה shecht is
legitimate? אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, so
this is going to be the heart of the question of 'is
a שחיטה shechita, that doesn't make the meat fit still considered a
שחיטה?' shechita. Where do you get this from? So where do you
say that it should
count? גמר שחיטה שחיטה משחוטי חוץ. Gemar shechita shechita mishchutei chutz. From
slaughtering outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. It says if you take
an animal and you שחיטה shechita it outside, the תורה Torah uses
the word ושחט. v'shachat. And by אותו ואת בנו Oso Ve'es Beno
it uses the word don't תשחטו, tishchatu, don't slaughter them. So it's
the same verb of שחטה. shachata. And when you שחיטה shechita a
קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you can't eat the
meat. So the same way the ושחט v'shachat by there means even
if the meat cannot be eaten, the ושחט v'shachat by אותו ואת
בנו Oso Ve'es Beno also means even if the meat cannot be
eaten. מה התם שחיטה שאינה ראויה שמה שחיטה, Mah hasam shechita she'eina
re'uya shemah shechita, the same way slaughtering a קרבן korban out of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the meat is not fit and the
תורה Torah still calls it—uses the verb ושחט. v'shachat. אף הכא נמי,
Af hacha nami, here too by אותו ואת בנו Oso Ve'es Beno
in the last פרק, perek, the mother and the child, even though
it says שחיטה, shechita. שחיטה שאינה ראויה שמה שחיטה. shechita she'eina re'uya
shemah shechita. Even if it's not fit, it's still considered שחיטה. shechita,
That seems to be a good argument. The תורה Torah says the
word ושחט v'shachat even in times where it definitely means that the
שחיטה shechita. is—the meat is not fit. ורבי שמעון, V'Rabbi Shimon, how
about רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says it doesn't count by אותו
ואת בנו? Oso Ve'es Beno? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's his reasoning?
So אמר רבי מני בר פטיש, Amar Rabbi Mani Bar Patish, גמר
מטבוח טבח והכן. gmar mi-tvo'ach tevach ve-hachein.
It says by יוסף Yosef right when his brothers come to visit
him and they don't realize who he is, anyway, he says to
the person over his household, טבוח טבח והכן, tvo'ach tevach ve-hachein,
slaughter the meat and get it ready, כי אתי יאכלו האנשים בצהרים,
ki iti yochlu ha-anashim ba-tzohorayim, they're going to eat with me in
the afternoon. So you see it talks about slaughtering and it talks
about eating. Okay, so מה להלן שחיטה ראויה, ma lehalan shechita ra'uya,
the same way there the slaughtering is that the food is going
to be able to be eaten, אף כאן, af kan, here too,
whenever the Torah talks about שחיטה shechting it means שחיטה ראויה, shechita
ra'uya, the food is going to be eaten. Now that seems like
quite a stretch, there it's not a מצוה, mitzvah, it doesn't even
use the verb ושחט, veshachat, which is what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say. ולרבי מאיר נמי ליגמר מטבוח, U-le-Rabbi Meir nami ligmor
mi-tvo'ach, why not learn from that verb which talks about eating the
meat? דנין שחיטה משחיטה, danin shechita mi-shechita, you use the same, no,
if it says the verb ושחט, veshachat, you use from other places
that it has the same verb of שחיטה. shechita ואין דנין שחיטה
מטביחה, ve-ein danin shechita mi-tvicha,
you don't link it to a verb that doesn't even use the
same verb, it uses the verb טבוח tvo'ach and not שחוט. shachot.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי נפקא מינה, mai nafka mina, who
cares if the word is a little different? התנא דבי רבי ישמעאל,
Ha-tanna d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, we learn in the house of Rabbi Ishmael,
ושב הכהן ובא הכהן, ve-shav ha-kohein u-va ha-kohein, this is talking about
when the כהן kohein visits the house of צרעת tzara'at and determines
its status and what gets done with it, and the גמרא Gemara
is going to make a גזירה שוה gezerah shavah from one verse
that says ושב, ve-shav, he returns, and the other verse that says
ובא, u-va, he comes, because whether he returns to the house or
comes to the house it's the same basic idea and is able
to connect those two paragraphs because of the ושב ve-shav and the
ובא u-va are essentially the same concept. And the גמרא Gemara always
likes to quote this as an example that when you're making a
גזירה שוה, gezerah shavah, you don't need the exact same word. As
long as conceptually it's the same, it's enough to make a גזירה
שוה. gezerah shavah. זו היא שיבה זו היא ביאה, Zo hi shiva
zo hi bia, returning and coming is the same. So you see
we can make a גזירה שוה, gezerah shavah, so why not link
it to the word טבוח, tvo'ach, which is essentially the same? So
the גמרא Gemara says, no, הני מילי היכא דליכא דדמי ליה. hanei
milei heicha de-leika de-dami lei. If there's nothing competing for, you know,
nothing else more similar, then you can compare words that are roughly
the same. אבל איכא דדמי ליה, aval eika de-dami lei, if there's
an identical word, מדדמי ליה ילפינן, mi-de-dami lei yalfinan, you learn it
from the identical word. So this is a very simple point, right?
How does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say a שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita
she'eina ra'uya counts? Because, I mean רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, because when
the Torah speaks about שחיטה, shechita a קרבן korban out of the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, a שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita she'eina ra'uya, it
uses the verb ושחט, veshachat, so we see even when it doesn't
make the meat fit, that counts as a שחיטה. shechita
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, so that's a pretty powerful argument to learn
from the verb ושחט, veshachat, how would רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon respond?
נמי ליגמר משחוטי חוץ, Nami ligmar mi-shechutei chutz,
why not learn from שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz outside the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, even when it's not fit, it counts? So his answer
would say, no, דנין חולין מחולין ואין דנין חולין מקדשים. danin chulin
mi-chulin ve-ein danin chulin mi-kodashim. I don't want to learn from קרבנות,
korbanos, קרבנות korbanos is a totally different category. שחיטה shechita a child
and a mother is the same, is non-קרבנות korbanos or not necessarily
קרבנות, korbanos, and therefore I refuse to learn from the world of
קרבנות. korbanot. Okay. לרבי מאיר, Le-Rabbi Meir, what would רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir say back? הכי השתא אותו ואת בנו בקדשים מי לא נהיגי.
Hachi hashta oso ve-es beno be-kodashim mi lo nahigi. Are you telling
about אותו ואת בנו Oso Ve'es Beno also applies to קדשים, kodashim,
it's not limited to חולין, chulin, but it also applies to קדשים?
kodashim? היינו דקאמר רבי חייא, Hainu de-ka-amar Rabbi Chiyya, that's what רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiyya said, רע רבי דבריו של רבי מאיר באותו ואת
בנו ושנה בלשון חכמים. ra Rabbi devarav shel Rabbi Meir be-Oso Ve'es
Beno ve-shanah bi-leshon chachamim.
He thought that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir had a nice strong position
by אותו ואת בנו. Oso Ve'es Beno. The Torah uses the verb
ושחט. veshachat. ושחט Veshachat is used by קרבנות korbanot outside of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash even when it's not fit. So you see
even a שחיטה shechita. that is not fit, okay, and that is
relevant to learn because אותו ואת בנו Oso Ve'es Beno applies even
to קרבנות. korbanot. So therefore we would like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
Now the other explanation, meaning even beyond all the פסוקים, pesukim, a
way to make it even sharper as we're going to see in
a minute is that the reason covering the blood is different and
it has to be שחיטה ראויה shechita ra'uya is there the verse
ends by saying ושפך
את דמו אשר יאכל, ve-shafach es damo asher ye'achel, that you are
slaughtering that you are capturing you know you are taking an animal
that will be eaten. So there it explicitly mentions will be eaten.
So maybe a simpler way to step away from all these verses
for a moment is to say normally a שחיטה shechita that's not
fit is still as a שחיטה shechita? and counts, and that's אותו
ואת בנו Oso Ve'es Beno and
that's the standard. The standard is a שחיטה shechita, that's not fit
counts as a שחיטה. shechita But by covering the blood, since the
verse speaks about meat that will be eaten, there we're saying the
שחיטה shechita actually has to be fit. Let's just see that and
then I'll take the question. Okay, so
מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר בכיסוי הדם, mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Meir be-khisuy ha-dam,
why does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say by covering the blood it
does not have to be fit, שחיטה? shechita אמר ריש לקיש גמר
שפיכה שפיכה משחוטי חוץ, Amar Reish Lakish gmar shfichah shfichah mi-shechutei chutz,
because as we've already said the שחוטי חוץ, shechutei chutz, קרבנות korbanot
outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is not fit, and there it
also speaks about spilling blood. The phrase it uses is if you
שחט a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, the Torah
says דם שפך, dam shafach, it's like you spilled blood. And by
covering the blood it says ושפך את דמו, ve-shafach es damo, it
uses the verse to spill blood. מה להלן שחיטה שאינה ראויה שמה
שחיטה, Ma lehalan shechita she'eina ra'uya shema shechita,
the same way by קרבן korban out of the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash it counts as a שחיטה, shechita אף כאן שחיטה שאינה ראויה
שמה שחיטה, af kan shechita she'eina ra'uya shema shechita, here too as
well. ולרבי שמעון, U-le-Rabbi Shimon, and this becomes the key, even beyond
all the... Even if in general you might argue שחיטה שאינה ראויה
shechita she'einah r'uyah counts, here it says אשר יאכל. asher ye'achel. If
somebody traps אשר יצוד ציד חיה או עוף אשר יאכל, asher yatzud
tzeid chaya o of asher ye'achel, traps an animal that will be
eaten. So כתיב, ksiv, so it means something that is fit to
be eaten and the שחיטה shechita therefore has to be fit. רבי
מאיר, Rebbi Meir, how would רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir respond back? ההוא
למיעוט עוף טמא הוא דאתא. hahu l'mi'utei of tamei hu d'ata. No,
it's coming to say that it's a non-kosher animal. Not that if
it was a טריפה treifa or something came to mess up to
make the שחיטה shechita not work. It was fundamentally a non-kosher animal,
that's what it's excluding. But not that the שחיטה shechita has to
make the meat fit for consumption. רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, what would
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon say back? עוף טמא מאי טעמא? of tamei
mai ta'ama? What's the reason you're excluding non-kosher animals? דלאו בר אכילה
הוא d'lav bar achilah hu
because you can't eat them. So טריפה נמי לאו בר אכילה היא,
treifa nami lav bar achilah hi, so anything you can't eat. Fine,
we'll exclude non-kosher animals as well, but the Torah's emphasis here is
that the שחיטה shechita has to be so that you will consume,
make it possible to consume the food. My question yesterday, we're going
to see this later today if not tomorrow, that even if your
intention is not to consume the food, like you just want the
blood of the animal or something like that, it doesn't matter. It's
not based about your intention, but it's based that the food has
to be fit to be eaten. The meat has to be fit.
So that's what we're saying, that here the Torah explicitly speaks about
the food about being able to be eaten, and therefore the שחיטה
shechita has to be fit. So where were we? והיינו דאמר רבי
חייא בר אבא, v'hainu d'amar Rebbi Chiya bar Abba, that's what רבי
חייא Rebbi Chiya said, ראה רבי דבריו של רבי שמעון בכיסוי הדם
ושל חכמים. ra'ah Rebbi d'varav shel Rebbi Shimon b'kissui hadam v'shel chachamim.
That's why here by covering the blood, the sages say that if
it's not fit you don't cover the blood because here it makes
sense to rule like רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. So the easier way
to step back from all the verses is to say that רבי's
Rebbi basic position is as a general rule, even if the שחיטה
shechita, does not make the meat forbidden, it counts as an act
of שחיטה shechita, for אותו ואת בנו oto v'et beno and for
other things in הלכה. But here since the Torah speaks about a
חיה or bird which will be eaten, here you only have to
cover the blood if the שחיטה shechita made the meat able to
be eaten. And therefore here the sages become the ones who say,
you know, that if it's not fit then you do not have
to cover the blood. אמר רבי אבא amar Rebbi Abba said רבי
אבא, Rebbi Abba, לא לכל אמר רבי מאיר
שחיטה שאינה ראויה שמה שחיטה. lo l'chol amar Rebbi Meir shechita she'einah
r'uyah shmah shechita. You spoke until now about רבי Rebbi splitting his
vote. It's not only about רבי Rebbi splitting his vote. Even רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir who says that a שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'einah
r'uyah counts has not, did not say it for all
purposes. שמודה רבי מאיר שאינה מתרתה באכילה, shemodeh Rebbi Meir she'einah matirtah
b'achilah, which almost is like self-evident. If the שחיטה shechita is אינה
ראויה einah r'uyah you still can't eat the meat. So he doesn't
really say it's a שחיטה, shechita of course, that would be sort
of a little circular. It's a non-fit שחיטה, shechita but anyway. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to ask what was the point of
that statement. Okay. ולא לכל אמר רבי שמעון שחיטה שאינה ראויה לאו
שמה שחיטה, v'lo l'chol amar Rebbi Shimon shechita she'einah r'uyah lav shmah
shechita, not for all purposes did רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon say it
doesn't count. מודה רבי שמעון שמתהרתה מידי נבילה. modeh Rebbi Shimon shemitahartah
miydei neveilah.
He would agree that it's still not like if you didn't do
a שחיטה shechita on the animal at all, it would be a
נבילה. neveilah. If you did a שחיטה shechita but it didn't make
it permissible, like you slaughtered it עבודה זרה, avoda zara, you slaughtered
it and it was a טריפה, treifa, it would still not be
considered a נבילה. neveilah. So again, that you would think that those
things are relatively evident. He's just saying don't get carried away. What
would be?
טריפה treifa or איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah like if you slaughtered a
שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. So it's something that was slaughtered, it's a
non-נבילה, neveilah, but the meat is forbidden in benefit because it was
עבודה זרה avoda zara or שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. But once there
was an act of שחיטה shechita done, it still is not a
נבילה. neveilah. Which is by the way the point being and maybe
here it gets to like conceptually what do we mean when we
say לאו שמה שחיטה. lav shmah shechita. The best way I think
to articulate it is it was an act of שחיטה shechita but
you know there was no היתר שחיטה heter shechita that took place,
right? The שחיטה shechita did not effect making the meat permissible. But
at least the act of שחיטה shechita was sufficient to get it
although by other things we would say well as long as you
have the act maybe that should be good enough and that's what
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says. So רבי, Rebbi, so that's what the
גמרא Gemara is saying. Even though רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon normally says
the act of שחיטה shechita. by itself is meaningless if it doesn't
make the meat permissible, by, to change it from not being considered
a נבילה, neveilah, it didn't die a death as a נבילה, neveilah,
the act of שחיטה shechita? was at least enough to say it's
not a נבילה. neveilah. Yes.
This strikes me that the cases of the משנה are fundamentally different
than אותו ואת בנו oto v'et beno in that אותו ואת בנו
oto v'et beno requires there to be שחיטה shechita for there, for
there to be איסור. issur. Right. The שחיטה shechita isn't done and
complete and כשר, kasher, there isn't אותו ואת בנו, oto v'et beno,
you just killed the animal.
How do you know? Only if you assume שחיטה שאינה ראויה לאו
שמה שחיטה. shechita she'einah r'uyah lav shmah shechita. What
do
you mean? No no no. You have to do a שחיטה. shechita...
What constitutes שחיטה? shechitah Absolutely.
But unlike the other cases where you have to do a, שחוטי
חוץ shchutei chutz or anything else like that
where the character of the
שחיטה shechitah. is קודשים kodashim at the outset because of the intention
or because of the location or anything else like that and I'm
going to say this act of שחיטה shechitah was never valid.
I don't understand. If what you're saying is, if what you're saying
is אותו ואת בנו oto v'et beno is different but you're saying
שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz is different because every act of שחיטה... shechitah
that שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz is automatically a שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechitah
she'eina ra'uyah, that's a good point and that you know רש"י ותוספות
Rashi and Tosafos whatever the גמרא Gemara, already discusses. But for example
there's a time let's say you steal a cow a sheep or
a cow and you שחט it where you pay four or five,
right? So there's a case where the act of שחיטה shechitah is
totally neutral in terms of the כשרות kashrus of the meat and
there's the same debate whether שחיטה שאינה ראויה שמה שחיטה shechitah she'eina
ra'uyah shemo shechitah or לא שמה שחיטה. lo shemo shechitah.
So it's also a case of שחיטה שאינה... shechitah she'eina...
if the animal happens to be a טריפה treifah or if you
happen to שחט it לעבודה זרה. l'avodah zarah. I think what you're
really trying to say though so is that שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz
is automatically שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechitah she'eina ra'uyah and that is a
legitimate point and that's the point already discussed.
No, the cases in the משנה are all cases where it's automatically,
עבודה זרה avodah zarah is going
to be every שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechitah she'eina ra'uyah.
Huh? Yes, that's every שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechitah she'eina ra'uyah. Right,
what's also to know is... No, no, no, no, no, you misunderstood.
We're not saying that standard אותו ואת בנו oso v'es beno is
a שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechitah she'eina ra'uyah. We're saying let's say when
you come around to שחט the cow, it happens to be a
טריפה, treifah, it happens or you're doing it לעבודה זרה, l'avodah zarah,
exactly these scenarios. Oh okay, I thought you were saying standard אותו
ואת בנו. oso v'es beno.
No, no, no, no, no.
No, we're saying that the scenario of שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechitah she'eina
ra'uyah like טריפה treifah or עבודה זרה avodah zarah and if you
did it in the context of אותו ואת בנו, oso v'es beno,
would you transgress or not? That's the case. Yes, right.
אשר יכוסה asher yichaseh would also mean at the time,
at that time was because let's say it didn't cover the blood
and then it became moldy. Right, yeah.
Okay, but anyway we normally mean halachically אשר יכוסה, asher yichaseh, but
yes, we do judge it at the time. Let's keep on going.
Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara, is going to say like this. אמר מר, Amar Mar,
let's look back at that statement. לא לכל אמר רבי מאיר שחיטה
שאינה ראויה שמה שחיטה. lo l'kol amar Rabbi Meir shechitah she'eina ra'uyah
shemo shechitah. מודה רבי מאיר שאין מתירתה באכילה. modeh Rabbi Meir she-ein
matirasa ba'achilah. He admits that even if it's not, that when it's
not fit it doesn't make it, when it's not מתירתה באכילה matirasa
ba'achilah it's not מתירתה באכילה. matirasa ba'achilah. It's a little tautologous. פשיטא,
Peshita, of course. טריפה בשחיטה מי משתריא? treifah b'shechitah mi mishtaryah? If
we take a simple case of שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechitah she'eina ra'uyah
like you שחט a טריפה, treifah, whoever thought that you could eat
a טריפה? treifah? It's forbidden to be eaten. So of course he's
not going to say that even though it's not fit it makes
the meat permissible to be eaten. That would anyway be circular, right?
I mean not circular, whatever, you know, it would be either tautologous
or a logical contradiction. So of course it doesn't make it permissible.
לא צריכא לשוחט את הטריפה. lo tzricha l'shochet es hatreifah. No, the
case that we're telling me this is, and this actually is an
interesting case, a very interesting case: you שחט an animal that is
a טריפה treifah ומצא בה בן תשע חי u'matza bah ben tesha
chai and you found in its womb, remember this, a fetus that
was nine months old. And if it's a nine-month-old fetus it has
a certain amount of independent status. It's debated whether it's considered to
be part of the mother or not.
So it has
to be a חי chai nine-month-old. So therefore there's the opinion in
the past that by the way רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir himself, that,
that requires a separate שחיטה. shechitah, The שחיטה shechitah of the mother
doesn't work. But even if you say the שחיטה shechitah. of the
mother works, it's not because it's just a natural appendage of the
mother. It's considered independent, but because it's in the mother's womb the
שחיטה shechitah of the mother also counts for it. Given that scenario,
here's what I might have thought. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina,
I might have thought to say, הואיל דאמר רבי מאיר שחיטה שאינה
ראויה שמה שחיטה, ho'il d'amar Rabbi Meir shechitah she'eina ra'uyah shemo shechitah,
since he says for other cases that if it's not fit it
still counts as a שחיטה, shechitah דהני לה שחיטת אמו, d'hani lei
shechitas imo,
so even though the mother was a טריפה, treifah, let the שחיטה
shechitah, count for the child in the mother's womb who is not
a טריפה, treifah, and let it count for that fetus, ולא לבעי
שחיטה, v'lo liba'ei shechitah, and not require a שחיטה. shechitah. קא משמע
לן kamashma lan that you can't. Now that actually is a very,
you know, sort of fascinating הוה אמינא hava amina because you could
say like this: you did an act of שחיטה shechitah on the
mother. The fetus is not, if it were a limb of the
mother then if the mother's a טריפה treifah the fetus is a
טריפה. treifah. But if it's not a limb of the mother, if
it's an independent life but it's in the mother's womb that, you
know, not independent, sort of dependent on the mother but it's still
its own life, and therefore we're saying that the שחיטה shechitah. of
the mother works for it, then you can conceptually say okay, so
it's its own thing. So the שחיטה, shechitah, you did an act
of שחיטה. shechitah Did it work for the mother? No, the mother's
a טריפה. treifah. That prevented the שחיטה shechitah from working for the
mother. Did it work for the fetus? The fetus isn't a טריפה.
treifah. So say the act applies to the fetus and therefore the
fetus should be okay, right? Because he normally says it's considered an
act. It's not that טריפה treifah stops us from calling it an
act of שחיטה. shechitah We call it an act of שחיטה, shechitah
it just wasn't מתיר matir the meat. So okay, maybe it didn't
מתיר matir, the meat of the mother, maybe it did מתיר, matir
the act of שחיטה shechitah applied to the fetus did מתיר matirs
the
fetus itself. So that's such a good הוה אמינא, hava amina, you
want to know what the answer to that is. Hopefully yeah, that's
a good point, let's say that. So that's he saying no, there
he would stop. Now why would he stop? Would he stop because
he would say that even in that case the only reason it
works on the fetus is because the fetus is a part of
the mother, or said a little differently, it works through the mother.
It's not that the act of שחיטה shechitah, is applied to the
fetus, but the effect of שחיטה shechitah is applied to the fetus.
If the שחיטה shechitah, מתיר matirs the mother, it מתיר whatever's inside
of the mother. So it's not where we're applying the act of
שחיטה shechitah to the fetus but the effect of the שחיטה, shechitah
the status change that the שחיטה shechitah effects. And therefore since it
doesn't affect that status change by the mother, it can't affect it
by the child. But it's a nice, it's an interesting little הוה
אמינא hava amina and therefore we have to say no, there רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir would draw the line.
Yes, Dave. So the simple question is why do we have different
standards for when the fetus is considered a part of the mother,
when the fetus is not considered part of the mother?
So it would seem that for the purpose of טריפה treifa and
שחיטה, shechitah why you're at different points on that spectrum of dependence
and independence? Right, so that's actually, so that's, so because because you
could say, because we know, meaning you're right, the simplest thing is
to say it's all or nothing. Either it's a part of the
mother and therefore the שחיטה shechitah works, or it's not and שחיטה
shechitah, doesn't work. And we know for example, actually the גמרא Gemara
is going to say in a minute, that how could you say
this all within רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
of the opinion that the שחיטה shechitah. of the mother by a
nine-month-old live fetus does not work for the fetus, so the whole
point is moot.
But anyway, the but the גמרא, Gemara I mean look, you know,
not only the גמרא, Gemara. I mean I think there's often a
fun part of learning גמרא Gemara is sort of exploring interesting sort
of middle positions. So it's possible to say that it's not just
a limb of the mother, so it's not a
טריפה, treifa, it is viable, it does have its own life, it
does have all of that, and therefore the טריפה treifa status doesn't
apply to it. But because it's still in a state of dependence
on the mother, if it's its own separate life but dependent on
the mother and contained within the mother's body, an act that's done
to the mother is considered to apply to the child as well.
And the question is do they have to have a theory as
to how to apply one aspect of dependence and another aspect of
independence?
I mean, I think that the things in the גמרא Gemara tend
to work more from starting with the cases and sort of a
sense that this case might be different and then sort of developing
the theory based on that. You sort of see that in certainly
at earlier stages there's less conceptual language. I mean in general in
law this is the
case. I mean look at משפטים Mishpatim in the תורה, Torah, it's
a lot of this case, this case, this ox gored, so the
practical application sort of starts first and then the
abstractions sort of come at a later time, which is why אביי
ורבא, Abaye ve-Rava, you know, which are very late, often talk in
the most abstractions in the גמרא. But there is an interesting way
to distinguish this case. You know we have it by the way
if a mother goes to the מקוה, mikveh, is converting and she
has a fetus inside of her, it applies to the child. So
it might not be that you're saying it's one unit, but just
it's enough somehow related, dependent and related, that it applies. Yes.
I think this gives another possible way to explain it that might
be simpler, just from the משנה's categorizations, that it's lumped השוחט ונמצא
טריפה ha-shochet ve-nimtza treifa in the same category as all the other
external presences at the outset being the key because that's the thing
that makes שחיטה shechitah the physical action not actually accomplish שחיטה shechitah
the process as we normally call it.
Yes, but we are doing it with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who
normally says there still is an act of שחיטה, shechitah so this
הוה אמינא hava amina is a fascinating הוה אמינא. hava amina. Let
it be an act and let it apply to the fetus. No
questions, we have six minutes left and we're way behind. Okay,
so the גמרא says like this. קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan.
ותסברא, ve-tisbara,
how could you even say that that was a הוה אמינא? hava
amina? והאמר רבי מאיר, ve-ha-amar Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
the one who says בן פקועה טעון שחיטה ben pekuah taun shechitah
that a בן פקועה ben pekuah which is a nine-month-old live fetus
needs its own שחיטה. shechitah So this whole הוה אמינא hava amina
is moot because he never says the שחיטה shechitah of the mother
works for the fetus. גמרא says לא צריכא דרבי. lo tzericha de-Rabbi.
Now remember we're not talking about רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir per se,
we're talking about רבי Rabbi who's entitled to split his vote. So
he סבר לה כרבי מאיר וסבר לה כרבנן. savar lah ke-Rabbi Meir
ve-savar lah ke-rabbanan. So he holds like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir in
the sense that and like the rabbis in different areas. Let's see.
סבר לה כרבי מאיר דאמר שחיטה שאינה ראויה שמה שחיטה. savar lah
ke-Rabbi Meir de-amar shechitah she-einah reuyah shemah shechitah. He generally holds like
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir as we said that's רבי's Rabbi default, that
a שחיטה shechitah that is not fit still counts. וסבר לה כרבנן
ve-savar lah ke-rabbanan and he also holds like the rabbis as we
know from the סתם משניות stam mishnayot in the earlier דאמר שחיטת
אמו מטהרתו de-amar shechitat imo metaherato that the שחיטה shechitah of the
mother works for the fetus, even the nine-month-old fetus.
So כיון דאמרי רבנן שחיטת אמו מטהרתו, keivan de-amri rabbanan shechitat imo
metaherato, so now רבי Rabbi has to decide what is he going
to do in this case where he normally holds the שחיטה shechitah.
of the mother works for the fetus, he normally holds the שחיטה
shechitah that's not fit counts, what if the mother is a טריפה,
treifa, will the שחיטה shechitah still work for the fetus? So כיון
דאמרי רבנן שחיטת אמו מטהרתו, keivan de-amri rabbanan shechitat imo metaherato, תהני
ליה שחיטת אמו, tehani leh shechitat imo, let the שחיטה shechitah of
the mother count for the fetus even if the mother's a טריפה,
treifa, ולא ליבעי שחיטה, ve-lo livai shechitah, not require שחיטה. shechitah. קא
משמע לן ka mashma lan
that nevertheless the היתר heter of the fetus comes through the היתר
heter of the mother and you don't just apply the שחיטה shechitah.
act directly to the fetus. And therefore that's where רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir would draw the line. We're not going to take that שחיטה
shechitah and apply it independently to the fetus. Okay, so that's where
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir agrees. ולא לכל אמר רבי שמעון שחיטה שאינה
ראויה לאו שמה שחיטה, ve-lo le-chol amar Rabbi Shimon shechitah she-einah reuyah
lav shemah shechitah, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon not for all purposes
says a not fit שחיטה shechitah is meaningless, it's not like you
didn't check it at all. מודה רבי שמעון שמטהרתו מידי נבילה, modeh
Rabbi Shimon she-metaherato midei nevelah, at least it's not a נבילה. nevelah.
Okay, at least that's the whole difference between a נבילה nevelah and
a טריפה treifa is that a טריפה treifa had an act of
a שחיטה. shechitah So although he says for other things it doesn't.
It doesn't count, at least it counted to say that it's not
a נבילה. neveilah. מאי פשיטא mai pashita obvious, דאמר רב הונא אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב ואמרי לה במתניתא תנא d'amar Rav Huna amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav ve'amrei lah be'masnisa tana or some say we
taught in the ברייתא, baraisa, וכי ימות מן הבהמה veki yamut min
habehemah if an animal dies it says then the carcass causes טומאה,
tumah, it's a נבילה. neveilah. מקצת מן הבהמה miktzat min habehemah
so it's limiting. מקצת בהמה מטמאה miktzat behemah metamei only some animals
cause טומאה, tumah, death of some, only some deaths cause טומאה, tumah,
ומקצת בהמה אינה מטמאה u'miktzat behemah einah metamei and some deaths do
not. ואיזו ve'eizo which death does not cause טומאה? tumah? זו טריפה
ששחטה, zo treifah sheshachatah, if he שחט a טריפה. treifah. So nobody,
everybody agrees that the whole difference between a טריפה treifah and a
נבילה neveilah is whether you had an act of שחיטה. shechitah. So
although he says for other things it doesn't count, it counts to
say that this isn't a נבילה. neveilah. It says no, צריכה לשחוט
את הטריפה והיא חולין בעזרה. tzerichah lishchot es hatreifah vehi chulin ba'azarah.
Ha! You know
another reason why it was a שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechitah she'einah re'uyah.
You שחט a טריפה treifah and it also happened to be an
animal in the בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, okay, a non-קרבן. korban. דתניא,
detanya, השוחט את הטריפה וכן השוחט ונמצאת טריפה. hashocheit es hatreifah vechein
hashocheit venimtzes treifah. You שחט an animal that's a טריפה, treifah, either
you knew it or you didn't know it. זה וזה חולין בעזרה
zeh vezeh chulin ba'azarah and it's חולין בעזרה. chulin ba'azarah. So have
you made the animal, if you שחט חולין chulin in the בית
המקדש, beis hamikdash, you can't eat the meat. But that's because you
did an act of שחיטה shechitah on a חולין בעזרה. chulin ba'azarah.
This is a שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechitah she'einah re'uyah because the animal's
a טריפה. treifah. So since the animal is a טריפה, treifah, you
did not make do a שחיטה shechitah of חולין chulin in the
בית המקדש beis hamikdash and therefore the meat is still permissible in
benefit. You can't eat it because it's a טריפה, treifah, but it's
still permissible in benefit. You did not transgress חולין בעזרה. chulin ba'azarah.
That means you can still use it. Right, well that's the שחיטה
שאינה ראויה shechitah she'einah re'uyah question. Since it was a טריפה, treifah,
it didn't count as a שחיטה shechitah, and you didn't transgress חולין
בעזרה. chulin ba'azarah. So רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon who says שחיטה שאינה
ראויה shechitah she'einah re'uyah doesn't count,
מתיר בהנאה mattir bahana'ah allows benefit because he says you didn't do
an act of שחיטה. shechitah, וחכמים אוסרים ve'chachamim osrin and the rabbis,
who is רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, says it counts as שחיטה shechitah
and therefore you שחט חולין chulin in the בית המקדש beis hamikdash
and therefore you can't get benefit. So here's what I would have
thought. Now רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says that this animal was not
חולין בעזרה chulin ba'azarah because it was a שחיטת טריפה. shechitas treifah.
סלקא דעתך אמינא salka da'atach amina I would have thought, הוא דאמר
hu de'amar רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon מותר בהנאה, muttar bahana'ah, since he
says you can get benefit, it wasn't considered a שחיטה shechitah in
the עזרה azarah because it was a טריפה. treifah. אמר לאו שחיטה
כלל amar lav shechitah klal in this case where they coincided, in
order to get you off the hook for חולין בעזרה chulin ba'azarah
I'm going to have to say this wasn't a שחיטה, shechitah right?
Because it was a טריפה. treifah. Once I'm saying it wasn't a
שחיטה, shechitah ממידי נבילה נמי לא מטהרה mimidei neveilah nami lo metaherah
tell me that I can't split my vote. If I'm already saying
that from the חולין בעזרה chulin ba'azarah perspective you didn't do a
שחיטה shechitah and you're off the hook, so I have to treat
it like whole no שחיטה shechitah occurred at all and like the
animal is a
נבילה. neveilah. קמשמע לן kamashma lan that you're able to split your
vote. You're able to say that from the חולין בעזרה chulin ba'azarah
perspective it was not a good שחיטה shechitah because it didn't make
the meat permissible and therefore you're off the hook, but from the
question of נבילה neveilah versus טריפה, treifah, at the end of the
day you did an act of שחיטה on an animal. Whenever you
do an act of שחיטה on an animal, you stop it from
being a נבילה neveilah even though that שחיטה act is meaningless from
חולין בעזרה chulin ba'azarah and you're off the hook, it's meaningful enough
to say the animal did not die a violent death or a
natural death, it died a שחיטה death and therefore it is not
a נבילה. neveilah. Okay, to be continued tomorrow. We are got close
to catching up.
Bye.